A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Education and Public Policy Program (EPP), Energy Policy Project Files FA535
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Education and Public Policy Program (EPP), Energy Policy Project Files
1971-1974
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA535
2.62 Cubic Feet 2 standard record storage boxes.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Scope and Contents
Primarily contains correspondence, reports and administrative materials.
Arrangement
Arranged in 3 series:
1. Administrative Files.
2. S. David Freeman Files.
3. EPP Reports.
Biographical / Historical
The Energy Policy Project (EPP) was a Ford Foundation Delegated Authority Project (DAP) that sought to research and analyze energy policy. The EPP lasted from 1972 to 1975, and in 1974, published its final report, A Time to Choose: America's Energy Future. In addition to the final report, the EPP published 19 project studies. The Foundation spent $4,150,000 for the project. Ford Foundation Resources and Environment Program Officer Edward Ames managed the project within the Foundation, and S. David Freeman was appointed as project director. Freeman had previously worked in the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA), and after his leadership of the EPP, he was appointed chairman of the Tennessee Valley Authority (TVA) by President Jimmy Carter in 1978 and later held leadership positions in public utilities corporations like the New York Power Authority and the Los Angeles Department of Water and Power.
The EPP originated from a proposal the Ford Foundation Resources and Environment Program made for a program of energy studies in 1971. The Foundation's interest in the energy field preceded the EPP. It had made several energy related grants between 1968 and 1971. The EPP was active during the 1973 oil crisis, and as an independent group in Washington D.C. concerned with energy policy alternatives, it played an educational and advisory role to Congress, parts of the Executive branch, and various public interest groups.
Chief criticisms of the EPP and its A Time to Choose report centered around arguments about lack of objectivity and low quality analysis (An Evaluation of the Energy Policy Project, September 1975, Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 6262-9286 (FA739C), Report 006648).
- Administrative Files, 1971-1974; I
  - The Book Re: Energy Policy Project, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - The Book -- Ballinger Publishing Company Re: EPP Report, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Book Chapters and Associated Studies -- Potential Output, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Briefings, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Energy Policy Project -- Press Releases, 1972 May-December (Box 1)
  - Energy Policy Project -- Library (creation and expansion of), 1972 (Box 1)
  - Energy Policy Project Study Guide -- Comments and Critiques, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Energy Policy Project Study Guide -- List of Recipients, 1972 November 8 (Box 1)
  - "Energy Policy Report" -- Numbers 1-4, 1972 August-1973 August (Box 1)
  - Prospectus and Reports Re: Purpose and Creation of Energy Policy Project, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Public Information Film -- Guggenheim Productions, Inc., 1973 (Box 1)
  - Public Information Film -- Guggenheim Productions -- Script, 1974 March 13 (Box 1)
  - Public Information Program, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Public Information Program -- Memorandum to Energy Policy Project Advisory Board, 1972 September 11 (Box 1)
  - Public Information Program -- Stuart Finley Production Company Re: EPP Film, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Public Information Program -- Tentative Information Plan, 1972 June 21 (Box 1)
  - Special Consultants, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - University of Oklahoma Data Bank, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars and Other Agencies -- Correspondence Re: EPP Study Guide and Project Administration, 1972 (Box 1)
- S. David Freeman Files, 1972; II
  - Interoffice Memoranda, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Freeman Reading/Correspondence File, 1972 May-November (Box 1)
  - Freeman Reading/Correspondence File, 1972 December (Box 1)
- EPP Reports, 1973-1974; III
  - "A Citizen's Guide to Energy", 1973 (Box 2)
  - "Studies in Energy Tax Policy" Edited by Gerard M. Brannon (1 of 5), 1973 (Box 2)
  - "Studies in Energy Tax Policy" Edited by Gerard M. Brannon (2 of 5), 1973 (Box 2)
  - "Studies in Energy Tax Policy" Edited by Gerard M. Brannon (3 of 5), 1973 (Box 2)
  - "Studies in Energy Tax Policy" Edited by Gerard M. Brannon (4 of 5), 1973 (Box 2)
  - "Studies in Energy Tax Policy" Edited by Gerard M. Brannon (5 of 5), 1973 (Box 2)
  - Perspective on Power: A Study of the Regulation and Pricing of Electric Power" by Edward Berlin, Charles Cicchetti, William Gillen, edited by Carole Grossman (1 of 2), 1974 January (Box 2)
  - Perspective on Power: A Study of the Regulation and Pricing of Electric Power" by Edward Berlin, Charles Cicchetti, William Gillen, edited by Carole Grossman (2 of 2), 1974 January (Box 2)
  - "Economic Analysis of Alternative Energy Growth Patterns, 1975-2000" by Edward A. Hudson, 1974 May 21 (Box 2)
  - "Potential Energy Conservation from Recycling Metals in Urban Solid Wastes" by William E. Franklin, David Bendersky, Wiliam R. Park, Robert G. Hunt, 1974 May 30 (Box 2)
  - "U.S. Energy Policy and Economic Growth, 1975-2000" by Edward A. Hudson and Dale W. Jorgenson, 1974 June (Box 2)
  - "A Proposal for a U.S. Energy R and D Policy" by J. Herbert Hollomon, 1974 July (Box 2)
  - "Health Effects of Energy Systems" by the American Public Health Association (1 of 2), 1974 August (Box 2)
  - "Health Effects of Energy Systems" by the American Public Health Association (2 of 2), 1974 August (Box 2)
  - "New Energy Technologies for Building: Institutional Problems and Solutions" by Richard Schoen, Jerome Weingart, Alan Hirshberg, edited by Jane Stein (1 of 2), 1974 September (Box 2)
  - "New Energy Technologies for Building: Institutional Problems and Solutions" by Richard Schoen, Jerome Weingart, Alan Hirshberg, edited by Jane Stein (2 of 2), 1974 September (Box 2)
  - "Energy Thrift in Urban Transportation: Options for the Future" by Margaret Fulton Fels and Michael J. Munson, 1974 October (Box 2)
  - Study of the Public Health Implications of a Plutonium Energy Economy, incl. report, "Radioactivity in Plutonium, Americium and Curium in Nuclear Reactor Fuel" by Thomas H. Pigford, 1974 (Box 2)